[music]
>> Welcome to Business Central Launch
Edition 2026 release wave one and
welcome to our session what's new in
fixed assets. My name is Alexander
Totovic. I am product manager and I have
my colleague with me today.
My name is George and I'm a developer.
So thank you George.
We can start
with the business value
because we didn't deliver
uh recently and we do not deliver so
often some new functionalities related
to fixed assets. So idea with these new
functionalities what you will see in a
minute is to improve compliance for
global customers, to make more accurate
tax planning and financial reporting and
reduce needs for custom extensions
because some new regulations are coming
or they exist in some countries and
earlier only one way you could do it is
if you customize.
So what is exactly? We introduce new
depreciation method. So now in a W1 in a
base app global base app you will find
new depreciation model as a bonus
depreciation method.
>> [snorts]
>> This is official name. We will call this
bonus depreciation but other names
depending from country to country you
can use additional first year
depreciation, investment bonus
depreciation in Australia and New
Zealand,
168K depreciation in United States,
investment incentive deduction first
year capital allowance and so on so on.
So different namings across different
countries but this is everything about
one common solution. What does it mean?
Bonus depreciation is accelerated
depreciation method that allows
businesses to deduct specific percentage
of asset cost in the first year
in a place in a service. So that means
in the first year you can deduct whole
amount or you can deduct
for example 50 60%
depending what you are low or what this
is required by the law and other
the rest of
fixed asset amount will be applicable
for regular rules
through other years of depreciation. So
this is how it will work. You can
accelerate depreciation immediately,
take a specific amount and after that
continue with a regular depreciation.
So now George please explain us about
bonus depreciation how we can set up and
few other things.
>> Yes. So
bonus depreciation
works well with all the other
depreciation methods and it is set up on
the fixed asset setup page.
There are two fields, one for the
percentage and one for the eligibility
date. It is the effective date when
when this rule applies. That means that
all assets that are placed in service
after that date are eligible for bonus
depreciation.
What it means it means that
the first depreciation after the
acquiring
is the bonus depreciation and from then
on
the normal depreciation method
continues.
So you you set it up on fixed asset
setup and then you can opt in to use it
or not on each fixed asset depreciation
book.
It is entirely driven by the by the
depreciation starting date field which
is the date when the the the asset is
placed in service in Business Central.
We will show you how it works in a
moment and just to mention that for
reporting we have added a few more
fields on the FA depreciation books
page.
They are hidden by default so you can
customize them onto the page and use
them for reporting by opening this page
in Excel.
So let's start with a demo.
And let's see here
in the fixed asset setup
you have two two new fields, one for
very defined
bonus depreciation percentage
and the second one for the effective
date. These are typically communicated
to the accountant by the government.
They are defined in the law.
And this is the maximum
percentage you can give. You can also of
course give less
but
this is the maximum and this is the the
date that drives eligibility. All assets
that are placed in service after this
date are eligible.
Then let's look at this
fixed asset
that is acquired but its depreciation
has not started yet.
We have a depreciation starting date
1st of January 27 that is higher than
the May 25th 2025
on the fixed asset setup page. So this
asset is eligible
for bonus depreciation and here we have
also added a few fields on the fixed
asset card
where you can see acquisition cost, you
can see bonus depreciation applied, how
much bonus depreciation was applied to
this asset.
And here you have the toggle whether or
not
to use the bonus depreciation. As soon
as you set a depreciation starting date
that is higher than effective date on
the setup
it will be set to true but for the
purpose of the demos
I've turned it off just so you can see
the difference.
So let's let's first turn it off for
this asset.
And then run
calculate depreciation report.
This is the report that calculates
periodically calculates depreciation
amounts.
And let's
let's say that you want to
Let's say you want to calculate the in
the first month of the depreciation
period for this asset.
It generates journal lines
with this amount. That is your first
depreciation. That is the
without bonus depreciation.
So let's look at the difference. It was
333.
Let's delete these lines and turn on
bonus depreciation.
So when you turn it on and run the
report
>> [snorts]
>> for this asset
>> you get you get an extra journal line
and that is the bonus depreciation. That
is 20%
of the 8,000 which was acquisition cost
for this asset.
And then the first depreciation is taken
with this amount deducted.
So you can see that the first
depreciation is a bit lower because we
have already deducted the 20%.
after
the acquiring of the asset.
Then we can look at the preview.
So you get you get an you get a ledger
entry for the bonus depreciation
and you get a ledger entry for the
normal depreciation.
Let's post this.
And here you can then see on the asset
you can see that bonus depreciation was
applied
that acquisition cost was 8,000 and that
current book value is
is 6,133. So that that includes both the
bonus depreciation and the depreciation.
And in the let's look at the page
depreciation books.
Here you can see I I have already
personalized this page to include these
four new fields.
You can you can filter your asset
fixed asset depreciation books to those
that use or don't use bonus
depreciation. You can see their
acquisition cost, you can see how much
bonus was applied
and you can see that their current
accumulated depreciation.
Yep. So that concludes the demo.
Thank you George.
And this is about what is new in fixed
assets. So we have this new
functionality, new depreciation model
and we are close to finish this session.
Before we close this session I would
like to remind you all these links. You
can find many interesting information
there.
Subscribe to our LinkedIn profile to be
updated all the time or
of course subscribe and watch our
YouTube channel to find all BC LE
sessions and other recordings there as
well.
So thank you for watching this video and
thank you for using Business Central.
Thank you George for joining me for this
session. Thank you.